A Guide to the Papers of Michael Ryan, 1957-1990
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Michael Ryan 1957-1990
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10963
This collection consists of ca. 4,000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access is controlled by the depositor or his designee. Those wishing access to the collection must furnish the Director of Special Collections a memorandum outlining their academic background, scope of project, importance of this collection to that project and any publication plans. The Director will forward the request to the depositor or, in his absence, his designee, Doreen Gildroy.
Acquisition Information
This collection was loaned to the University of Virginia Library by Michael Ryan of Santa Monica, California, on June 21, 1990.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of the papers of American poet Michael Ryan (1946- ), ca. 4,000 items (21 Hollinger boxes, and 1 cubic of printed material, 8 linear feet), 1957-1990, containing correspondence; manuscripts of articles, poems, and books, both by Michael Ryan and others; printed material; cassette tapes of poetry readings by Michael Ryan; and notebooks, examinations, and papers pertaining to Ryan's undergraduate years at the University of Notre Dame.
Ryan was educated at the University of Notre Dame (A.B. 1968), Claremont Graduate School (M.A. 1970), and the University of Iowa (M.F.A. 1972; Ph.D. 1974). He has taught in the Creative Writing Programs and English Departments of the University of Iowa, Southern Methodist University, Goddard College, Princeton University, and Warren Wilson College, as well as giving some lectures at the University of Virginia. Some of the awards and honors that Ryan has received include: the Yale Series of Younger Poets Award, Texas Institute of Letters Prize, and Nominee, National Book Award, all for Threats Instead of Trees (1973, 1974); Fellowship in Creative Writing, National Endowment for the Arts (1976-1977); Residence, Yaddo (1975 & 1977); the Virginia Prize for Poetry from Virginia Commission for the Arts for God Hunger (1987); the Whiting Writing Award (1987); and the Emily Clark Balch Prize for Poetry, for "Meeting Cheever" (1989).
Organization
The first series of this collection consists of the literary manuscripts of Michael Ryan, divided into three subseries: books; articles, lectures, etc.; and poetry. The books subseries includes the manuscripts for his University of Iowa thesis "The Blind Swimmer;" his books of poetry including God Hunger(1989), In Winter(1981), and Threats Instead of Trees(1974); and an unfinished novel. Ryan's articles and lectures concerning poetry are arranged alphabetically by title and include publication in such periodicals as The New England Review & Breadloaf Quarterly, The American Poetry Review, Crazyhorse Poetry and Prose, and Poetry. Also in the second subseries are interviews with Stanley Kunitz and Alan Dugan and an introduction for Ann Beattie and Raymond Carver.
The last subseries includes individual poems by Michael Ryan, each foldered separately and arranged alphabetically by title. The numerous working drafts present for many of Ryan's poems will benefit anyone seeking to study Ryan's method of poetry composition.
The second series contains poetry, short stories, essays, a novel, and articles submitted to Ryan by his friends and colleagues for advice, comments and literary criticism.
Correspondence with friends, colleagues, and other contemporary poets comprises the third series. Correspondents with several letters to their credit have their own folder and are listed in the box listing; those with less material have been filed alphabetically in general correspondence folders but have also been listed in the box listing.
The fourth series of topical and miscellaneous material contains personal papers, biographical information concerning Ryan, legal papers, grant applications, printed material, papers concerning Ryan's part- time work at the MFA Writing Program at Warren Wilson College, and papers pertaining to Ryan's undergraduate work at the University of Notre Dame. Papers in this series relating to his literary career include a copy of his own comments about his poetry to Stanley Kunitz, comments regarding In Winter and God Hunger, and cassettes of Ryan reading and discussing his own poetry in Ohio, Arizona, Virginia, and elsewhere.
Contents List
- Series I: Writings by Michael Ryan
  - Subseries A: Books
    - "The Blind Swimmer" A Thesis by Michael Ryan submitted to the Department of English in the Graduate College of The University of Iowa, supervised by Marvin Bell 1972 May, TMs (EC) (Box 1)
    - God Hunger ca. 1989, 2 TMs (EC) (Box 1)
    - God Hunger ca. 1989, 2 TMs (EC) (Box 1)
    - God Hunger with comments by Stephen Berg 1987 Aug, TMs (EC) (Box 1)
    - God Hunger with comments by Ellen Bryant Voigt 1987 Apr, TMs (EC) (Box 1)
    - God Hunger with corrections 1989 Aug, TMs (EC) (Box 1)
    - God Hunger 1989 Aug, 2 Page Proofs (EC) (Box 1)
    - God Hunger- unrevised and unpublished page proofs 1989, Bound Page Proofs (Box 1)
    - God Hunger- sample layouts and book jackets 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - In Winter ca. 1981, TMs (Box 1)
    - In Winter- uncorrected bound page proofs 1981, Bound Page Proofs (Box 1)
    - In Winter- Published Hardback Version 1981, Printed (Box 2)
    - "A Little of That" - first draft, with corrections n.d., TMs (EC) (Box 2)
    - "Foreword" by Stanley Kunitz to Threats Instead of Trees1973 Oct, TMsS (Box 2)
    - Threats Instead of Trees- original working copy ca. 1973, TMs (EC) (Box 2)
    - Threats Instead of Trees- original manuscript ca. 1973, TMs (EC) (Box 2)
    - Threats Instead of Trees ca. 1973, TMs (EC) (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Threats Instead of Trees [ca. 1974], Galley Proofs (Box 2)
    - Threats Instead of Trees- uncorrected proofs [ca. 1974], Page Proofs (Box 2)
  - Subseries B: Articles, Lectures, etc.
    - The American Poetry Review Symposium Statement 1984 (Box 3)
    - "A Dark Gray Flame" in New England Review and Bread Loaf Quarterly1984 Summer (Box 3)
    - "Difficulty and Contemporary Poetry" in The Associated Writing Programs Newsletterca. 1988 (Box 3)
    - "Disclosures of Poetry: On Wallace Stevens and 'The Idea of Order at Key West" in The American Poetry Review1982 (Box 3)
    - "Eliot's Assumptions" in Crazyhorse Poetry and Prose1984, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - "First Love" n.d. (Box 3)
    - "Flaubert in Florida" in New England Review and Bread Loaf Quarterly1984 (Box 3)
    - "Flaubert in Florida" in New England Review and Bread Loaf Quarterly1984 (Box 4)
    - Interview with Stanley Kunitz n.d. (Box 4)
    - Interview with Alan Dugan n.d. (Box 4)
    - Introduction for Ann Beattie and Ray Carver n.d. (Box 4)
    - "Isolation and Apocalypse" in The Worchester Review1985 (Box 4)
    - "Leaving the Tour" in The American Poetry Review1983-1984, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - "Life Between Scylla and Charybdis" in The American Poetry Review1985 (Box 4)
    - "The Literary Dictator" n.d. (Box 4)
    - "Modern American Poetics" [Making Poems - Essays by Modern American Poets on the Craft of Poetry] n.d., (4 folders) (Box 5)
    - "On the Nature of Poetry" 1980-1984 (Box 5)
    - "A Phantasmagoria" in Singular Voices1982 Oct (Box 5)
    - "Poetry and the Audience" in The American Poetry Review1988, (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - Poetry Techniques - Handouts & Notes n.d. (Box 6)
    - "Symposium of Poets on T.S. Eliot Introduction in The Southern Review1985 (Box 6)
    - "A Talk on Wallace Stevens" in Poetry1979 Sep (Box 6)
    - Untitled Notes for an Article n.d. (Box 6)
  - Subseries C: Poetry
    - "Adagio" 1968 (Box 7)
    - "The Amazing Pissed-Off M & M" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "Analysis" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "Analysis and the Buddy System" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "Another Flight" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "Anticipating the Moment" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "Anti-elegy" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "An Apology to Patty" 1980 (Box 7)
    - "The Apprehensible World" 1988 (Box 7)
    - "Ars Poetica" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "The Art of Composition" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "At My Father's Death" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "Barren Poem" [1975] & n.d. (Box 7)
    - "Be Dumb" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "The Blind Swimmer" [1973] & n.d. (Box 7)
    - "Blue Corridor" 1982 (Box 7)
    - "Boy 'Carrying-In' Bottles in Glass Works" 1988 (Box 7)
    - "Break-in" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "A Brief Skirmish" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "Bunny" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "A Burglary" 1989, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - "The Children's Room" [1973] & n.d. (Box 7)
    - "Clean Living Poem" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "Clouds" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "Committed" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "Conditions of Snowbound" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "A Connubial Transaction" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "Consider A Move" [1977] & n.d. (Box 7)
    - "The Convert" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "County Fair" 1989 (Box 7)
    - "Crank Call" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "Crossing the Mojave in a VW Bus" n.d. (Box 7)
    - "Crossroads Inn" 1983-1987 (Box 7)
    - "The Crown of Frogs" 1989 (Box 7)
    - "The Date" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "The Death Machine" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Death-Mask" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Deduction & Corollary" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Diner, 4 AM" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Directions" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Disclaimer with Qualifications" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "The Ditch" 1988 & n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Do the Dead-End Split" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Dream Song" [1971] & n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Dreams of Murder" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Driving in the Rockies" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Drowning" [1972] & n.d. (Box 8)
    - "An Eastern Poet Foresees His Death in Hollywood" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Elegy" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Family Chronicle on My Grandfather's Death" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Field Trip" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Fire" 1986 (Box 8)
    - "First Exercise" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Flight" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "For Daedalus" 1967 (Box 8)
    - "The Gladiator" 1985 (Box 8)
    - " God Hunger" 1988 (Box 8)
    - "Hangman" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Her Report" 1989 (Box 8)
    - "Hitchhike" 1968 (Box 8)
    - "Hitting Fungoes" [1971] & n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Honor Thy Father" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "House" [1973] & n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Houseflies" 1989 (Box 8)
    - "How the Winter is Gone" [1972] & n.d. (Box 8)
    - "I Gets Alot" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "In the Bookstore" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "In the Rockies" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Intrusion" 1966 (Box 8)
    - " In Winter" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "It: A Dream Fragment" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "The Janitor's Coffin" [1975] & n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Larkinesque" 1984 (Box 8)
    - "The Last Night We Were" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Learning of Sterility" [1971] & n.d. (Box 8)
    - "The Leaving" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Leaving a Lover" [1971] & n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Letter from an Institution" [1971-1975] & n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Letter to a Lover" 1970 (Box 8)
    - "Little Political Poem" [1973] & n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Love Handles" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Love Moves to Salt Flats" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Love Song With Animals" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Mad Song" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Marriage; A Print; The Break" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Masturbation & Epithalamion for Patricia" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "The Meeting" [1973] & n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Meeting Cheever" 1989 (Box 8)
    - "Midnight Spin" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Milk the Mouse" 1989 (Box 8)
    - "Moonlight" 1988 (Box 8)
    - "Mouth" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Multiple Puns, Terminal Growths" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "My Dream by Henry James" 1983 (Box 8)
    - (Box 8)
    - "My Other Self" n.d. (Box 8)
    - "Next Project for You" n.d. (Box 9)
    - "Nighttime Pastoral" n.d. (Box 9)
    - "Not the End of the World" 1988 (Box 9)
    - "Of Mary Tyrone" n.d. (Box 9)
    - "An Old Book in Florence" n.d. (Box 9)
    - "On A Window of Glass" n.d. (Box 9)
    - "On the Impossibility of Seeing the Star" [1971] & n.d. (Box 9)
    - "One" 1988 (Box 9)
    - "One Stop in the Snake House" n.d. (Box 9)
    - "Palinode" 1988 (Box 9)
    - "Parting Advice" n.d. (Box 9)
    - "Parting Letter to Thanksgiving" n.d. (Box 9)
    - "Passion" 1988 (Box 9)
    - "The Past" [1978] & n.d. (Box 9)
    - "Pastoral" [1973] & n.d. (Box 9)
    - "Pedestrian Pastoral" 1988 (Box 9)
    - "Pigskin" n.d., (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - "Piles and the Man" n.d. (Box 9)
    - "The Plumber" n.d. (Box 9)
    - "Poem for Men Only" [1973] & n.d. (Box 9)
    - "Poem on a first line by Thom Gunn" n.d. (Box 9)
    - "Portrait of a Lady" 1982 (Box 9)
    - "A Postcard from Italy" (Poem Begun on A Postcard) 1982 (Box 9)
    - "Posthumous Letter from a Victim of the Inquisition" n.d. (Box 9)
    - "Prayer to Theodore Roethke" n.d. (Box 9)
    - "Prothalamion for Patricia" [1973 ?] & n.d. (Box 9)
    - "QED: The Chicago Express" n.d. (Box 9)
    - "Revenge" n.d. (Box 9)
    - "Rush Hour" n.d. (Box 9)
    - "Ryan's Diner" n.d. (Box 9)
    - "The Sacrifice" n.d. (Box 9)
    - "San Dimas House of Detention" n.d. (Box 9)
    - "The Scene and the Place" n.d. (Box 9)
    - "Sea Worms" 1988 (Box 9)
    - "Sergio" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Sexual Energy" [1973] & n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Smoke" 1989 (Box 10)
    - "A Smoker's Dream n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Snake-eyes" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Snow" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Soft Shoot Becomes a Winter Tree" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Sometimes Metaphysical" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Sonnet for Cindy" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Spider Plant" 1988 (Box 10)
    - "A Splinter" 1988 (Box 10)
    - "Standing Invitation" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Stone Paperweight" 1989 (Box 10)
    - "Stunt Man" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Sunday Drive" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Switchblade" 1985 (Box 10)
    - "Tanglewood for H" 1984 (Box 10)
    - "That First Time" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Thinking of You" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "This is a Poem for the Dead" [1975] & n.d. (Box 10)
    - "This is Why" 1984 (Box 10)
    - "This Winter" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Through A Crack" 1988 (Box 10)
    - "To A Waitress in the Hamburg Inn" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "A Tourist's Guide to Las Vegas" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Tourists on Paros" 1983 (Box 10)
    - "Transplant in a Catholic Hospital" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Tricky Dick and the Revolution" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "TV Room at the Children's Hospice" 1989 (Box 10)
    - "Two Answers" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Two For Pat" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Two Rides On a Bike" 1989 (Box 10)
    - "Wake Up" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "We All Have Our Delusions" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Weekend Sailor" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "What Keeps You Thinking" [1973] & n.d. (Box 10)
    - "When I Was Conceived" [1978] & n.d. (Box 10)
    - "The Wind, the Door, the Exit" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Winter Drought" 1985 (Box 10)
    - "The World's Biggest Turd: A Scenario" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Your First Drowning" n.d. (Box 10)
    - "Your Own Image" [1975] & n.d. (Box 10)
    - Early Poetry - Untitled and Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 10)
- Series II: Writings by Other Authors
  - Picturing Will by Ann Beattie ca. 1989, (4 folders) (Box 11)
  - Short Stories from Where You'll Find Me & Other Stories by Ann Beattie ca. 1986 (Box 11)
  - In It by Stephen Berg 1983-1985, 3 TMssS (Box 11)
  - In It by Stephen Berg 1986, Galley & Page (Box 11)
  - Proofs (Box 11)
  - "Love Song" by Stephen Berg n.d. (Box 11)
  - "O I'm A Human Being - Versions of Eskimo Songs" by Stephen Berg 1983 (Box 12)
  - "The Painter Who Loved Gray" by Stephen Berg n.d. (Box 12)
  - Individual Poems by Stephen Berg ca. 1982-1989 (Box 12)
  - Short Stories by Stephen Berg ca. 1983-1989, (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - "Poetry's Old Air" by Marianne Boruch 1989 (Box 12)
  - Black Dog, Red Dog by Stephen Dobyns ca. 1984 (Box 12)
  - "Caverns of Darkness" by Stephen Dobyns, with a poem "Spring Rain" 1980 (Box 12)
  - The Illustrations by Norman Dubie ca. 1977 (Box 12)
  - In the Dead of the Night by Norman Dubie ca. 1975 (Box 12)
  - Poems by Gunter Eich translated by Michael Ryan n.d. (Box 12)
  - Poems by Karen Fish n.d. (Box 12)
  - Elsewhere Children by Reginald Gibbons 1985 (Box 12)
  - Essays by Reginald Gibbons 1985 & n.d. (Box 12)
  - Poems by Louise Gluck 1986-1988, n.d. (Box 13)
  - "Postmodern Poetic Form: A Theory" by Jonathan Holden 1983 (Box 13)
  - "Apache" by David Huddle 1982 (Box 13)
  - The Fish-Wife by Cynthia Huntington ca. 1986 (Box 13)
  - Poems and Essays by Stanley Kunitz 1984-1985, n.d. (Box 13)
  - Poetry by Thomas Lux n.d. (Box 13)
  - The Pose of Happiness by Gail Mazur 1983 (Box 13)
  - The Tulip Man by Linda McCarriston 1982 (Box 13)
  - ["Hearing Voices"] by Dennis McFarland n.d. (Box 13)
  - Cities in Motion by Sylvia Moss 1985 (Box 13)
  - Wyndmere Poems by Carol Muske 1984 (Box 13)
  - Getting by 20 Below Zero by Jack Myers 1972 (Box 13)
  - Poems by Steve Orlen 1985 (Box 13)
  - Burning the Empty Nests by Gregory Orr 1973 (Box 13)
  - "Voyages and Desire" by Gregory Orr 1984, n.d. (Box 13)
  - Poems, An Essay and a Review by Robert Pinsky, including several reviews of his book The Want Bone1990, n.d. (Box 14)
  - Poems by Stanley Plumly [ca. 1972 ?] (Box 14)
  - "Fall River" by David Rivard 1985 (Box 14)
  - Poems by Ernest Sandeen n.d. (Box 14)
  - Permanent Change by John Skoyles 1990 (Box 14)
  - Poems by Maura Stanton n.d. (Box 14)
  - The Forces of Plenty by Ellen Bryant Voigt 1983 (Box 14)
  - The Lotus Flowers by Ellen Bryant Voigt, including several miscellaneous poems 1987 (Box 14)
  - Raised Underground and The Glass House by Renate Wood 1985 (Box 14)
  - "Strategies of Semblance in the Works of William Butler Yeats and Rainer Maria Rilke" by Renate Wood 1983 (Box 14)
  - Work by Renate Wood submitted for the MFA Program for Writers and evaluted by Michael Ryan 1983 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous Poetry n.d. (Box 14)
- Series III: Correspondence
  - Correspondence: Joan Aleshire 1983-1989 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence: Charles Baxter 1986-1990 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence: Ann Beattie 1983-1990 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence: Stephen Berg 1981-1989, n.d., (6 folders) (Box 15)
  - Correspondence: Raymond Carver 1982-1986 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence: Peter Davison 1986-1989 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence: Carl Dennis 1988-1990 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence: Stephen Dobyns 1982-1989 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence: Reginald Gibbons 1981-1990 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence: Louise Gluck 1981-1989, n.d. (Box 16)
  - Correspondence: Allen & Judith Grossman 1983-1990 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence: Donald Hall 1982 & 1987 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence: Seamus Heaney 1983-1989 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence: Edward Hirsch 1986-1989 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence: Marie Howe 1989 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence: David Huddle 1982-1983 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence: Diane Johnson 1983-1990 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence: Donald Justice 1977-1987 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence: Judy Karasik 1981-1983, 1990 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence: Stanley Kunitz 1984-1989 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence: Sydney Lea n.d. (Box 16)
  - Correspondence: Thomas Lux 1981-1989 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence: Paul Mariani 1984, 1989 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence: Gail Mazur 1982-1989 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence: Linda McCarriston 1983-1990 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence: Lisel Mueller 1984-1989 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence: Carol Muske 1982-1990 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence: The New Yorker1982-1990 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: John Nims 1982-1983 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: Robert Pinsky 1984-1989 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: David Rivard 1987-1989 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: Liz Rosenberg 1981-1990 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: Michael Ryan 1968-1990 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: Ernest Sandeen 1968-1988 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: Grace Schulman 1982-1990 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: Jason Shinder 1982 & 1989 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: Michelle Blake Simons 1981-1986 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: Roger Skillings 1982-1989 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: John Skoyles 1981-1989 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: The Southern Review Anniversary Issue re T.S. Eliot 1984-1985 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: Viking Penguin, Inc./Charles Verrill 1987-1990 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: Ellen Bryant Voigt 1982-1990 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: Theodore Weiss 1983-1989 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: Whiting Foundation 1987-1989 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: Geoffrey Wolff 1982-1990 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: Tobias Wolff 1985-1989 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: Renate & William Wood 1982-1987 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: A-C 1982-1990 (Box 18)
  - Correspondents include: Michael Anania; Kathleen Anderson; Rocio Aragon; Estelle Baird; David Baker; Judith Baumel; Stephen Bauer; Jill Bialosky; Mary Biggs; Staige Blackford; Robert Bly; David Bonanno; Marianne [Boruch ?]; Maris Brason; John C. Broderick; Jane Brox; Juanita Brunk; Stanley Burnshaw; Edward T. Chase; Alan Cheuse; Michael Cuddihy; and Mark Cox (Box 18)
  - Correspondence: D-F 1986-1990 (Box 18)
  - Correspondents include: Phillip Dacey; Christopher de Vinck; Eve Donner; Stephen Dunn: Stuart Dybek; John Donoghue; Paul Engle; Roger [Fanning]; Carol Fischler (see Liz Rosenberg); Karen Fish; and Jim Frazee (Box 18)
  - Correspondence: G 1981-1989 (Box 18)
  - Correspondents include: Jonathan Galassi; Tess Gallagher; Greg Gatenby; Gloria Gerritz; Matthew Gilbert; Barry Goldenshon; Roger Greenwald; Debra Gregerman; and David Groff (Box 18)
  - Correspondence: H-J 1982-1990 (Box 18)
  - Correspondents include: Bob Hass; Kitty Hamilton; Hope Harris; Donna Hedman; William Heyen; Omus Hirshbein; Conrad Hilberry; Gregory Hill; Brenda Hilman; Jonathan Holden; Jennifer Howard; Cynthia Huntington; John [Jacoby ?]; Timothy Jahns; Mark Jarman; and Robert Jebb (Box 18)
  - Correspondence: K-L 1981-1990 (Box 18)
  - Correspondents include: Peter Kardon; Michael Keller; Chris Kennedy; Rod Kessler; Michael Klein; P.A. Larkin; Wendy Larsen; Swiftly Lazar; Don Lee; David Lehman; Wendy Lesser; Walt Litz; and Margot Livesey (Box 18)
  - Correspondence: M 1970-1990 (Box 18)
  - Correspondents include: Bob Malsberger; Charles E. Mann; Gary Margots; Steve [Margulies ?]; Shelley Mason; Cleopatra Mathis; Forche Matthison; Heather McHugh; Ethelbert Miller; Fred Moramarco; Robert Morgan; Stanley Moss; Andrew Mossin; List Muracci; Kay Murphy; and Jack Myers (Box 18)
  - Correspondence: N-R 1970-1990 (Box 18)
  - Correspondents include: Josh Neufeld; Sharon Olds; Sharon Olinka; James Olney; Steve Orlen; Gregory Orr; Joyce Peseroff; Stanley Plumly; Ann Porotti; Francine Prose; Austin Quigley; Claude Rawson; Liam Rector; David Remnich; Paulette Roeske; Edwin Romand; Kenneth Rosen; Richard Russo; and Patricia Ryan (Box 18)
  - Correspondence: S 1983-1990 (Box 18)
  - Correspondents include: Ira Sadoff; David St. John; James Schley; Dennis Schmitz; Peter Sears; Jane Shore; Ilena Silverman; Greg Simon; Rebecca Sinkler; Carol Smitey; Dave Smith; Bill Spengemann; Shelby Staples and Carol Swezay (Box 18)
  - Correspondence: T-W, Z 1982-1990 (Box 18)
  - Correspondents include: Harold Taylor; Stephanie Terry; Jean Thompson; Dennis Vannatta; Nance Van Winckel; Roxanna Warren; James Walton; [Bruce ?] Weigl; Ken Weisner; David Weiss; Julia Wendell; C.K. Williams; Bill Witherup; David Wojahn; Robert Wrigley; and Gina Zeiler (Box 18)
  - Correspondence re Copyrights and Permissions 1970-1990 (Box 19)
  - Correspondence: Miscellaneous 1968-1990, n.d. (Box 19)
- Series IV: Topical & Miscellaneous
  - Awards 1987-1990 (Box 19)
  - Biographical Information 1981-1989, n.d. (Box 19)
  - Comments by Michael Ryan re his own poetry to Stanley Kunitz 1973 Aug-Sep (Box 19)
  - Comments re In Winter and God Hunger1981, 1986-1989 (Box 19)
  - Contracts and Legal Documents 1974-1990 (Box 19)
  - "Freedom and the Poet's Responsibility to Society" Symposium of The American Poetry Review& the American Poetry Center 1984 (Box 19)
  - Items removed from the copy of In Wintern.d. (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous Papers 1989-1990, n.d. (Box 19)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities Grant Application and the Fulbright-Hays Award Application 1979, 1985 (Box 19)
  - Personal Papers 1957-1981 (Box 19)
  - Printed Material 1968-1989, n.d. (Box 19)